The Tomb of the Cybermen
(Whopix fan edit)
赛博人的坟墓
(Whopix 粉丝剪辑版)
Stand by. Everybody down.
准备，所有人趴下
50 pounds for the first man
to open the doors.
第一个打开大门的奖励50英镑
Miss Kaftan, I must remind you
that I am the leader of the...
Kaftan 小姐，我必须得提醒你，我才是队长...
- What happened?  - I don't know.
- 发生了什么？  - 我不知道
Well, one thing for sure, he's not going to
collect 50 pounds from you or anybody else.
好了，有件事可以肯定，他没法从你这里拿走拿50英镑了
- Quiet. Quiet a minute.  - What's that?
- 安静，安静一下  - 什么声音？
Sounded like an engine.
听起来像是一种引擎
(WHOOSHING)
- Something came down there! Behind that ...
- OK, Viner. Slow down.
- 有什么东西降落了，在后面...  - 好，Viner，悠着点
- I'll take care of this. Jim!
- OK. I've got it!
- 我去看看。Jim!  - 好，我知道了
(LOW VOICES)
Hold it right there, friend.
停住别动，朋友
If you put it like that, I certainly will.
如果你要这样，我当然照作
Hear that, Professor? English.
听到了吗，教授？是英语
(PARRY) Yes. All right, Hopper.
是的。没事了，Hopper
Thank you.
谢谢你
Who are you and where are you from?
你们是谁，从哪里来？
And you'd better have a good story.
你们最好有一个好的说法
Maybe you'll not get one.
也许你们听不到
Listen, fella.
We're not playing games.
听着，伙计，我们不是在玩游戏
- You'd better listen to him.
- What's been happening over here?
- 你们最好听他的  - 这里发生了什么？
He was killed the moment you men  appeared.
他在你们出现的那一刻被杀了
Ah. And you think we did it?
啊，所以你们认为是我们干的？
Oh no, I can assure you, we had nothing
to do with the death of this man.
不，我可以保证，我们跟这个人的死没有关系
He appears to have been electrocuted.
他看着像是被电击了
Trying to open these doors, perhaps?
是在试图打开这道门吗，或许？
- He seems to know all the answers.
- A wiseguy!
- 他似乎知道所有的答案  - 一个聪明人！
I think this fellow must be
a member of a rival expedition.
我觉得这个家伙肯定是对手探险队的成员
(DOCTOR) Expedition?
探险队？
We've tried to keep it secret.
Unsuccessfully, now it appears.
我们试图保密的，现在看起来没成功
Archaeologist written all over him.
他全身都写着考古学家这几个字
- Really? Does it show?  - You see?
- 真的嘛？这么明显？  - 你看
It's impossible to keep a secret
in the scientific world.
在科学时间里几乎不可能保守住秘密
- Doctor, what do you mean?
- Tell them, go on, Doctor, tell them.
- 博士，你什么意思？  - 告诉他们吧，博士
No, not until they tell us
the purpose of their expedition.
不，除非他们先告诉我他们探险队的目标
This is an archaeological expedition.
这是一次考古探险
We are searching the universe
for the last remains of the Cybermen.
我们正在宇宙中寻找赛博人的最后遗迹
Cybermen? You mean to say they came from here?
赛博人？你是说他们来自这里？
Of course. Telos was their home.
当然，Telos 是他们的家
This is the entrance to their city.
这是通向他们城市的入口
We know they died out centuries ago,
我们知道他们几个世纪前就灭绝了
what we don't know is why they died out.
但我们不知道的是，他们为什么灭绝了
Callum, Rogers! Get him back to the rocket.
I'll be with you in a minute.
Callum, Rogers！来把他抬回火箭去，我很快回来找你们
That's that. Are you coming back
to the rocket with me, Professor?
就是这样。你跟我们回火箭吗，教授？
- What for?
- You're not going on with this, are you?
- 为什么回去？  - 你不打算继续了吧，是吗？
I don't know if these people had
anything to do with it or not,
我不知道这些人跟这事有没有关系
but one of my men was just been killed.
You're not paying that kind of money.
但我的一个人刚刚死了。你并不打算这种情况付钱
- Yes, I suppose that's quite true.
- You think it over.
- 是的，我觉得是这样  - 你想清楚了
Come on, let's go.
We'll wait for you at the ship.
快点，我们走，我们在飞船上等你们
The problem, I take it,
is to open these doors, right?
现在的问题，照我理解，是怎么打开门，对吧？
- Ha! Brilliant.  - That is the problem.
- 哈！高见  - 那就是问题
And we would prefer it, if you return
to wherever you came from.
而我们更愿意的是，你们从哪里来回那里去
- Not very friendly, are they?
- Do as he says.
- 他们不太友好，是吧？  - 按他说的做
That became impossible the moment
that name was mentioned - Cybermen.
那已经变得不可能了，因为那个名字被提到了 - 赛博人
Cybermen? What are they?
赛博人？是什么？
I knew they're here on the same quest!
我就知道，他们是为了同一个任务来这里的
No one would come here for any other reason?
就没有人因为别的原因来这个地方吗？
- We must stay!  - Doctor!
- 我们必须留下来！  - 博士！
Must we? I don't like
the look of those things at all.
必须吗？我完全不喜欢这些事情的样子
We shall stay and help you with your research.
我们会留下来，帮助你们进行研究
Perhaps we don't want help.
也许我们并不需要什么帮助
That's just it. You obviously do.
Now I'm sure we can agree.
这就是了，你们显然需要。我确定我们可以达成一致
- I can open those doors for you.
- It's our problem!
- 我能帮你们打开这道门  - 这是我们自己的事！
Can I suggest you take this ridiculous
expedition of yours off this planet!
我建议你们，把你们这个荒谬的探险从这个星球上带走!
It seems to me we have
as much right here as you have.
在我看来，我们在这里跟你们有一样的权利
Of course you have!
Mr Klieg, must I remind you again...
你们当然有！Klieg 先生，需要我再提醒你一次吗？
that you do not speak for this expedition?
I am its leader.
你并不能代表探险队说话。我才是队长
You and Miss Kaftan
are only here on sufferance.
你和 Kaftan 小姐在这里只是出于我们的宽容
- Thank you. And whose money is paying
for the hire of that rocket?
- (KAFTAN) Mine!
- 多谢提醒。为火箭雇人用的是谁的钱？  - 我的！
I thought I made it clear
that your financial support...
我想我明确过了，你们的经济支持...
did not entitle you to a say
in the running of this expedition!
并没有赋予你们在探险队运作上的发言权!
Of course. It was quite clear.
当然，你说得很清楚
Was it not, Eric?
不是吗，Eric？
Of course.
No one questions your leadership.
当然，没有人质疑你的领导权
Good. That's all settled.
好，那一切都解决了
- And now we shall open these doors.
- What...?
- 那现在我们去把门打开  - 怎么...？
- Careful, man!  - Doctor!
- 小心，朋友！  - 博士！
Perfectly safe now.
现在完全安全了
- You'll be killed!  - Don't touch him!
- 你会死的！  - 别碰他！
- It's beyond my strength.
- Let me, Doctor.
- 我力气不够  - 让我来，博士
I've not had much exercise lately.
我最近没怎么锻炼
Quite. I think here is a gentleman
who could open these doors for us.
是。我觉得这里有个先生可以帮我们把门打开
He is my servant.
I will not have him risk his life.
他是我的仆人，我不会允许他冒生命危险
Surely it was just for such a contingency like this
that you insisted we bring him with us.
就是为了这样的意外，你才坚持让我们把他带在队里的
There's no danger now.
Unless he's afraid.
现在没有危险了，除非他害怕
No, no. He's not afraid.
不不，他不害怕
- Come on.  - No. Wait!
- 快来  - 不，等等
I would be very careful in there
if I were you.
如果我是你，我进去会很小心的
Why weren't Toberman killed?
Why weren't you killed?
为什么 Toberman 没死？为什么你没死？
The poor fellow who died drained
all the electricity out of his body.
死去的那个可怜家伙，用他的身体把电都吸干了
It's perfectly safe to go in now.
现在进去完全安全了
We're wasting time.
我们在浪费时间
Of course. After you, Professor.
的确是。你先请，教授
But I'd still...
但我还是...
I'd still be very careful if I were you.
Very careful indeed.
如果我是你，我还是会非常小心，真的非常小心
Come on. Let's join them.
快来，跟他们一起
Come on, Victoria.
来吧，Victoria
You look very nice in that dress.
你穿着这条裙子非常漂亮
Thank you.
Don't you think it's a bit...?
谢谢你。你没觉得它有点..
Short? I shouldn't worry.
Look at Jamie's.
短吗？我就不担心。看看Jamie 的
I'll have you know that... Oh, aye.
我得让你知道...噢，是
Come along. Let's go and see
what the others are doing.
过来，我们去看看其他人在做什么
(VICTORIA)
Mercy! Just look at this place.
怜悯！看看这个地方
These controls are of earlier dynasties.
这些开关都是上个时代的
Not so early. Look, John...
没那么早。你看，John
I'm quite capable of making
my own deductions! Thank you.
我完全有能力自己来推断！谢谢你
All right.
好吧
Be careful. There might be danger.
小心，这可能有危险
Don't worry, with Toberman to guard me.
别担心，有 Toberman 护着我呢
What is more important is
to keep an eye on these strangers.
更重要的是，得盯着点这些陌生人
- I tried to...!
- Do not raise your voice.
- 我试图...  - 别那么大声
You will achieve nothing by shouting.
靠大喊大叫是什么也无法达成的
You look after the Doctor
and I will watch the girl.
你看着博士，我盯着这个女孩儿
- And the Scots boy?
- Leave him to Toberman.
- 那个苏格兰男孩儿呢？  - 把他留给 Toberman
Eh, Toberman?
嗯，Toberman？
- But you will be careful and discreet. Understand?
- I understand.
- 但你得小心谨慎点，明白吗？  - 明白
- Did you ever see the like of it, Doctor?
- Not exactly, Jamie, but very nearly.
- 你见过这样的吗，博士？  - 还没有，Jamie，不过很类似
(PARRY) Now that we're all here...
既然我们都在这里...
Now that we're all here, we'd better
take stock of the situation.
既然我们都在这里了, 我们最好评估一下情况
This appears to be a dead end.
这边似乎是条死路
The only way out is through that hatch.
唯一出去的路就是那个舱门
- Are there no doors?
- No. Apart from the entrance.
- 没有门吗？  - 没有，只有这个入口
- And the other two, of course.
- Two other doors?
- 和另外两个，当然了  - 另外还有两个？
Yes. One in that section
and one in that section over there.
是的，一个在这一段，还有一个在那边那段
Activated, I imagine, by this
simple logical system here.
激活方法，我估计，是用这边的简单符号逻辑系统
Here we are, I think.
就这里，我想
(BLEEPING)
Yes, splendid! A simple logical gate.
是的, 太棒了!一个简单的逻辑门
Doctor, you seem to be
very familiar with this place.
博士，你似乎非常熟悉这个地方
Not really. It's all based on symbolic logic.
还真不是，这全都是基于符号逻辑
The same as you use in computers.
跟你们在电脑里用的一样
The opening mechanism of this door -
an OR gate, as you call it.
打开这道门的机制，是一道或门，你们的叫法是这样的
Yes, I can see that, but how did you know
in the first place?
是的，我看得出来, 但你一开始是怎么知道的？
I use my own special technique.
我使用我自己的特殊技巧
Really? And may we know what that is?
真的？那可以告诉我们是什么吗？
Keeping my eyes open
and my mouth shut.
睁大眼睛，闭上嘴巴
We are too many to explore together.
I think we'd better divide up.
我们人太多了, 难以一起探索。我想我们最好分开
If you, Mr Viner, would take that door with...
如果你，Viner 先生，走那个门，与...
- Jamie.  - Jamie and Mr Haydon.
- 我叫Jamie  - 与Jamie 和 Haydon 先生一起
Mr Klieg, the Doctor and myself
will be a party.
Klieg，以及博士和我一队
- What about us?
- I think the women should better to remain here.
- 我们怎么办？  - 我觉得女人最好留在这里
Rubbish! We can make a party.
胡说！我们可以组一队
Certainly. With Toberman to guard us,
we need fear no one.
当然。有 Toberman 保护，我们谁也不怕了
Mr Klieg, will you take them with you?
Klieg 先生，你会带他们一起吗？
- I prefer to stay here.  - As you wish.
- 我情愿留在这里  - 随便你了
Mr Viner, will you go along with the women?
Viner 先生，你可以跟女人们一起走吗？
- If you like.
- Get back to the spacecraft by 16.30.
- 随你安排  - 要在16:30回到飞船
You all know the temperature drop at night,
你们都知道，气温会在晚间下降
so we'll meet back here at 16.25.
If anyone is missing...
所以我们在16:25回这里会合。如果有人失踪...
that gives us an hour to look for them
before we have to leave.
这可以给我们一个小时去寻找他们，之后就必须得离开了
Come on then. We might as well
try that opening over there.
那就来吧。我们可能得试试那边的开关
We'd better keep close together.
我们最好待在一起
I'm all right, thank you.
我没事，谢谢你
- Come on, Jamie.  - Right.
- 快来，Jamie  - 好
Now to concentrate on this, whatever it is.
现在聚焦一下这个东西，不管它是什么
This hatch must lead somewhere
这个舱门肯定通向某个地方
and there must be
some opening mechanism.
而且肯定有某种打开机制
What was that about
symbolic logic? Any ideas?
那跟符号逻辑有什么关系？谁知道？
No, not really.
不，不怎么知道
I think it's time
we gave Mr Klieg a chance
我看是时候给 Klieg 先生一个机会了
to show off his archaeological skills.
让他来炫耀一下他的考古技巧
Come on. Right in.
快来，进来了
Where's Toberman?
Toberman 去哪儿了？
I sent him to join the others.
我让他加入其他组了
We do not need protection
now that you are with us.
既然你跟我们在一起，我们不需要保护了
Yes. Well, shall we commence?
是的。怎样，我们开始吧？
Everything must be carefully
measured and recorded.
每样东西都必须精心测量、仔细记录
What is this room?
这是个什么房间
I don't know. Possibly this is
where the Cybermen are made.
我不知道。也许这是赛博人被造出来的地方
I wonder what this is.
我很好奇这是什么
Do you mind? You're in my way.
Just go over there.
抱歉，你妨碍到我了。去那边吧
Oh, fiddle!
噢，瞎搞
Could this not be the purpose of the room?
这可能是这个房间的目的吗？
Yes?
什么
A Cyberman would stand
in that form and be...
赛博人就站在那里面，然后就被...
Well, revitalised.
嗯，焕发生机了
Yes, that's reasonable.
是的，有道理
These projectors probably meant to fire in
some neuro-electric potential.
这些射枪很可能是用来注入神经电势能的
That's it. I think you're right.
是的，我觉得你说得对
Revitalising is just what I need.
我正好也需要重新焕发生机
Mercy! The Cybermen
must have been giants!/
天呐，赛博人一定都是巨人！
Well?
怎样？
The basis of this code
is binary to digital conversion,
这段编码的基础是二进制到数字转换
with an intervening step involving
a sort of Whitehead logic.
夹杂了一个中间步骤，这个步骤涉及某种怀特黑德逻辑
When this Bourrier series is complete,
then there is no more to be done.
当Bourrier系列完成的时候，就搞定了fixme
- Yes, but why do it at all?
- Really, Doctor?
- 是，但为什么要弄那个？  - 真的吗，博士？
For an archaeologist, you seem to
be curiously lacking in curiosity.
作一个考古学家，你居然缺乏好奇心
Some things are better left undone
and I have a feeling this is one of them.
有些东西最好别动，而我有种感觉，这就是其中之一
What do you mean by that?
这么说是什么意思？
- It's all too easy, isn't it?  - Easy?
- 所有这些都太容易了，是不？  - 容易？
I wouldn't call this an easy survey. Would you?
我不会把这称为容易的调查。你会？
Everything is designed to keep their secrets,
whatever they are, insoluble.
所有这些的设计目的，都是为了让他们的秘密无法解开
Insoluble? Oh, I wouldn't say that.
无法解开？噢，我不会这么说
Take this mathematical sequence for example.
I'm really no nearer to its solution.
拿这个数学序列来说，我真的离解开它还远着呢
I've tried every combination.
It's hardly call that easy.
我试了所有的组合了。真没法把这说是“容易”
Yes. Well, what you've done here
is mostly right.
是。不过，你在这里已经完成的绝大部分都是对的
- Thank you (!)
- You see, any progressive series
- 谢谢你  - 你看，任何递进的系列
can be converted into binary notation.
都可以被转换为二进制写法
If you take the sum of the integrets
如果你对整数求和
and express the result as a power series,
再将结果表达为幂数系列
then the indices show the basic binary blocks.
然后指数就会呈现基本的二元块了
(这一段完全不懂，瞎翻译，抱歉)
Only I wouldn't do it if I were you.
Oh, I really wouldn't do it.
只是我就不会这么做，如果我是你的话。噢，我真的不会
Of course! You're right!
当然！你是对的！
(LOW HUMMING)
Look! Sum between limits of one and 91
看！对1和91求和
integral into power series... Yes, yes!
积分到幂数系列，对了，对了！
Then you differentiate...
然后再进行差分...
You fool! Why couldn't you leave it alone?
你个蠢人！怎么你就不能别碰它？
- What's happening?  - I don't know.
- 怎么了？  - 我不知道
Perhaps the Cybermen aren't as
quite dormant as you imagine.
也许赛博人不像我们想的那样完全在休眠
Yes, we must find out
what's happened to the others.
是了，我们必须看看其他人怎么样了
- Is that all?  - Aye.
- 都试过了？  - 是
All except this big button here.
What does that do?
都试过了，除了这个大按钮，它是干什么的？
I'm not sure, but we'll find out.
我不确定，但我们会弄明白
I'm going to trace the source
of these shapes.
我打算跟踪一下这些形体的来源
There must be a projector somewhere.
肯定某个地方有个投射器
- When I give the word, press the button.
- The big one?
- 我喊的时候，就按那个按钮  - 大这个？
Yes. Maybe it works in conjunction with the others.
也许它要跟其它的一起才能生效
- Right. Ready when you are.
- OK. Go ahead.
- 好，等你准备好了  - 好，开始吧
- Jamie, don't touch that control!
- I already have.
- Jamie，别碰那个开关！  - 我已经碰了
- What's the matter, Doctor?
- Which one was it?
- 什么情况，博士  - 刚才是哪个？
Which one what?
哪个怎么了？